Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine and today we have an elementary level lesson in which we're going
我是Catherine，今天我们有一节初级课程，我们要
to talk about small talk.
聊聊闲聊这个话题。
That's right.
没错。
Today we're going to talk to an old friend and so we're going to give you some of the
今天我们要和一位老朋友聊天，所以我们会给大家一些
words and phrases you need to talk about your past or talk about how you have been.
谈论过去或近况所需的单词和短语。
So let's listen to today's dialogue and we'll be back in a moment to discuss it.
那么，让我们听听今天的对话，稍后回来讨论。
I hate coming to high school reunions.
我讨厌参加高中同学聚会。
It'll be great, honey.
会很好的，亲爱的。
We will get to see your old classmates and catch up to see how they've been doing.
我们会见到你的老同学，聊聊他们的近况。
Yeah, I guess so.
是啊，我想也是。
Oh look, there's Robert Matthews.
哦，看，那是Robert Matthews。
Rob.
Rob。
Hey, Bill.
嘿，Bill。
Wow.
哇。
Great to see you.
很高兴见到你。
Likewise.
我也是。
It's been a long time.
好久不见了。
This is my wife, Dorothy.
这是我妻子，Dorothy。
Pleasure to meet you.
很高兴认识你。
So Bill, how have you been?
那么Bill，你最近怎么样？
Can't complain.
还行吧。
We have two children who are in college and my business is going well.
我们有两个孩子在上大学，我的生意也不错。
How about you?
你呢？
Ah, you know me.
啊，你知道我的。
I'm a dedicated bachelor.
我是个坚定的单身汉。
I never married, although I do have a beautiful daughter with Mary.
我从未结婚，不过我和Mary确实有一个漂亮的女儿。
You remember her.
你还记得她吧。
We were high school sweethearts.
我们曾是高中时的恋人。
It didn't really work out between us, but I really can't complain either.
我们之间没成，不过我也没什么可抱怨的。
That's good.
那挺好的。
Have you seen Frank?
你见过Frank吗？
I was hoping he would come tonight.
我本来希望他今晚能来。
You didn't hear?
你没听说吗？
Frank passed away last year.
Frank去年去世了。
Are you serious?
你说真的吗？
Nah, I'm just janking your chain.
不，我逗你玩呢。
He'll be here soon.
他很快就到。
I saw him last week.
我上周见过他。
I was hoping he would show up.
我本来希望他能出现。
Alright we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's get started with our language takeaway.
那么现在开始我们的语言要点部分。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
The first phrase we have here in language takeaway is a very important one because it
语言要点里的第一个短语非常重要，因为它
is the setting for today's dialogue.
是今天对话的背景。
We are at a high school reunion.
我们在一个高中同学聚会上。
That's right.
没错。
So everyone knows what high school is, but a high school reunion is when you go back
大家都知道高中是什么，但高中同学聚会是指你毕业后
to your high school for a party maybe five years or ten years after you graduate.
五年或十年回到高中参加的一个派对。
So then you meet all your old friends from high school.
这样你就能见到所有高中时的老朋友。
You talk about how you have been and just meet up with everyone that maybe you haven't
你们聊聊近况，和那些可能很久没见的人
seen in a very long time.
聚一聚。
Exactly.
正是。
So a reunion usually happens every five years, ten years, or twenty years.
所以同学聚会通常每五年、十年或二十年举行一次。
It can happen at different times, but this is important because you can have many different
时间可以不同，但这很重要，因为你可以有各种不同的
kinds of reunions like a college reunion or a high school reunion.
聚会，比如大学同学聚会或高中同学聚会。
I've even heard of some people who had an elementary school reunion.
我甚至听说过有人办小学同学聚会。
Really?
真的吗？
Wow.
哇。
Imagine seeing your classmates when you were maybe ten years old.
想象一下见到你十岁时的同学。
I couldn't imagine.
我无法想象。
Alright so we're at a high school reunion and we are there because we're going to meet
好了，我们在一个高中同学聚会上，我们来这里是为了见
our old classmates and to catch up and see how they have been.
老同学，聊聊近况，看看他们过得怎么样。
Okay so this is exactly what you do at a reunion.
好的，这正是你在聚会上做的事。
You catch up with people that you maybe lost touch with, to catch up means to find out
你和那些可能失去联系的人叙旧，catch up的意思是了解
about what people have been doing since the last time you talked.
自上次交谈以来人们都在做什么。
So maybe Marco and I were classmates in high school and we haven't talked in ten years.
所以也许Marco和我是高中同学，我们十年没说话了。
I say, Marco, I want to catch up.
我说，Marco，我想和你叙叙旧。
I want to learn about what you do, who you married, where you work, things like that.
我想了解你做什么工作、娶了谁、在哪里工作之类的事情。
Right, so when two people get together to catch up, maybe it doesn't even have to be
对，所以当两个人聚在一起叙旧时，也许不一定需要
a very long time.
很长时间没见。
Maybe you haven't seen your friend for a week and so you want to get together, have a cup
也许你一周没见朋友了，所以你想聚一聚，喝杯
of coffee and catch up and see how the relationship has been going or how it works so you want
咖啡，聊聊近况，看看关系进展如何，所以你想
to catch up.
叙旧。
So you can say this in a very simple way, let's catch up or it's been nice to catch
所以你可以很简单地说，let's catch up 或者 it's been nice to catch
up.
up。
That's right.
没错。
Alright, moving on to our next word.
好了，继续看下一个词。
This guy Bill meets up with Robert Matthews and they're saying, hey, wow, great to see
这个叫Bill的家伙遇到了Robert Matthews，他们说，嘿，哇，很高兴见到
you and he answers by saying, likewise.
你和他回答时可以说“彼此彼此”。
So it's good to see you, likewise.
所以“很高兴见到你，彼此彼此”。
That means it's good to see you too.
意思是“我也很高兴见到你”。
So you don't have to repeat everything that person just said.
这样你就不用重复对方刚说的每一句话。
For example, if I just meet someone new and I say it's a pleasure to meet you, you can
比如，如果我刚认识一个人，说“很高兴认识你”，你可以
say?
说什么？
I could say likewise.
我可以说“彼此彼此”。
Because I don't want to say it's a pleasure to meet you too.
因为我不想说“我也很高兴认识你”。
That's so many words.
那太啰嗦了。
So likewise is a very short way to say all of those things.
所以“彼此彼此”是一个非常简短的方式来表达所有这些意思。
That's right.
没错。
So we were finding out about Robert Matthews and he says that, well, he is a dedicated
我们刚才在了解罗伯特·马修斯，他说他是一位
bachelor.
坚定的单身汉。
So a dedicated bachelor, what is a bachelor, Marco?
那么“坚定的单身汉”，什么是单身汉，马可？
So a bachelor is a person who is not married, a person who is single.
单身汉是指没有结婚的人，单身的人。
A man.
男人。
A woman cannot be a bachelor.
女人不能叫单身汉。
So a bachelor is specifically a man and he's not married and we often have a stereotype,
所以单身汉特指男人，他没有结婚，我们通常有一种刻板印象，
that means we have an idea of what a bachelor lives like.
也就是说我们对单身汉的生活有一种固有看法。
He has only beer in his refrigerator and he has many relationships and no wife.
他的冰箱里只有啤酒，有很多恋情，没有妻子。
That's right.
没错。
So a dedicated bachelor is a person who is not married and doesn't really seem to want
所以“坚定的单身汉”是指没有结婚，而且似乎并不想
to get married or any of this.
结婚或类似事情的人。
He wants to stay single.
他想保持单身。
Exactly.
正是。
Okay.
好的。
And well, to finish off, this guy Robert lied a little bit to Bill saying that Frank had
最后，这个叫罗伯特的人对比尔撒了个小谎，说弗兰克
passed away.
去世了。
That's really mean, but this phrase to pass away is very important and something we should
这真够损的，但“去世”这个短语非常重要，我们应该
talk about.
讨论一下。
So what does it mean to pass away?
那么“去世”是什么意思？
It's another way of saying he died.
这是“他死了”的另一种说法。
So it's nicer.
所以更委婉一些。
Yeah, it's a lot more subtle and nicer.
是的，更含蓄、更委婉。
So instead of saying Frank died, you say Frank passed away.
所以不说“弗兰克死了”，而说“弗兰克去世了”。
So you could say, you know, last year my grandmother passed away.
你可以说，比如，去年我奶奶去世了。
That's a way of saying that my grandmother died last year, but again, it's a lot nicer
这是说我奶奶去年过世了的一种方式，但同样，这是一种更委婉
way to say that.
的说法。
Yeah, because the word died can be a little bit too direct and too harsh.
是的，因为“死”这个词可能有点太直接、太刺耳。
So maybe saying my grandmother passed away last year, it's a nicer way of saying it.
所以也许说“我奶奶去年去世了”是一种更委婉的说法。
Okay.
好的。
So that's all the language takeaway you have.
这就是所有的语言要点。
Let's take a look at our dialogue again and we'll be back.
让我们再看一遍对话，然后回来。
I hate coming to high school reunions.
我讨厌参加高中同学聚会。
It'll be great, honey.
会很好的，亲爱的。
We will get to see your old classmates and catch up to see how they've been doing.
我们会见到你的老同学，聊聊他们最近怎么样。
Yeah, I guess so.
嗯，也许吧。
Oh look, there's Robert Matthews.
哦，看，那是罗伯特·马修斯。
Rob.
罗布。
Hey Bill.
嘿，比尔。
Wow.
哇。
Great to see you.
很高兴见到你。
Likewise.
彼此彼此。
It's been a long time.
好久不见了。
This is my wife, Dorothy.
这是我妻子，多萝西。
Pleasure to meet you.
很高兴认识你。
So Bill, how have you been?
比尔，你最近怎么样？
Can't complain.
还不错。
We have two children who are in college and my business is going well.
我们有两个孩子在上大学，我的生意也顺利。
How about you?
你呢？
Ah, you know me.
啊，你知道我的。
I'm a dedicated bachelor.
我是个坚定的单身汉。
I never married, although I do have a beautiful daughter with Mary.
我从没结过婚，虽然我和玛丽有一个漂亮的女儿。
You remember her.
你记得她吧。
We were high school sweethearts.
我们高中时是情侣。
It didn't really work out between us, but I really can't complain either.
我们之间没成，不过我也没什么可抱怨的。
That's good.
那挺好的。
Have you seen Frank?
你见到弗兰克了吗？
I was hoping he would come tonight.
我本来希望他今晚能来。
You didn't hear?
你没听说吗？
Frank passed away last year.
弗兰克去年去世了。
Are you serious?
你说真的吗？
Nah, I'm just janking your chain.
不，我只是在逗你玩。
He'll be here soon.
他很快就到。
I saw him last week.
我上周见过他。
He told me he would show up.
他告诉我他会来的。
Alright let's move on now to four key phrases on Fluency Builder.
好了，现在我们进入流利度构建的四个关键短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度构建。
So the focus of today's Fluency Builder is small talk.
今天流利度构建的重点是闲聊。
These are phrases you can use when you're at a reunion or a dinner, especially with
这些是你在同学聚会或晚宴上可以用的短语，尤其是和
people you don't know very well.
你不怎么熟悉的人。
So let's jump in and look at this first phrase.
那我们就直接进入正题，看看第一个短语。
Great to see you.
很高兴见到你。
That's right.
没错。
So he says, hey Bill, wow, great to see you.
所以他说，嘿，比尔，哇，很高兴见到你。
So this is a nice little opening phrase saying, wow, I'm really excited to see you.
这是一个很好的开场白，意思是，哇，我真的很高兴见到你。
I'm really happy to see you.
我真的很高兴见到你。
Exactly.
正是如此。
It means I'm happy.
意思是我很开心。
Look at you.
看看你。
Great to see you.
很高兴见到你。
You say this at the beginning of a conversation.
你在对话开始时说这句话。
That's right.
没错。
And actually Bill responded by saying likewise.
实际上比尔回答说“彼此彼此”。
So we talked about this.
我们之前讨论过这个。
He's saying, wow, great to see you too.
他在说，哇，我也很高兴见到你。
Then he continues by saying, it's been a long time.
然后他接着说，好久不见了。
This means that these two people, they have not seen each other in a very long time.
这意味着这两个人已经很久没见面了。
You can also say, it's been so long or it's been a long time.
你也可以说“好久不见”或“很久没见了”。
That means it's been a long time since we last saw each other.
意思是我们上次见面已经过去很久了。
That's right.
没错。
So Robert goes on to ask Bill.
所以罗伯特接着问比尔。
He says, well, you know, how have you been?
他说，嗯，你知道，你最近怎么样？
How are things?
情况如何？
Bill answers by saying, can't complain.
比尔回答说，没什么可抱怨的。
Okay.
好的。
So this is not grammatically correct.
这在语法上并不正确。
Normally you need a subject.
通常你需要一个主语。
I can't complain.
我没什么可抱怨的。
But when we're speaking in English and we're having a conversation like this, it's okay
但当我们用英语这样对话时，
to say just can't complain as a phrase.
只说“没什么可抱怨的”作为一个短语是可以的。
So he's saying, how have you been?
所以他在问，你最近怎么样？
Well, I can't complain.
嗯，我没什么可抱怨的。
Can't complain.
没什么可抱怨的。
That means nothing bad has happened.
意思是没发生什么坏事。
Things are okay.
一切还好。
Right.
对。
You're saying that things are good.
你在说情况不错。
They're not fantastic, but they're not bad either.
不是特别好，但也不差。
So you can't really complain.
所以你真的没什么可抱怨的。
So it's just a phrase where very directly you can say, oh, can't complain.
所以这是一个很直接的短语，你可以说，哦，没什么可抱怨的。
Everything's great.
一切都很好。
So you could even say this about other things.
你甚至可以用它来形容其他事情。
Like, you know, I asked John how his job was and he said, can't complain.
比如，你知道，我问约翰他的工作怎么样，他说，没什么可抱怨的。
Right.
对。
It's not great, but it's not bad.
不是很好，但也不差。
Right.
对。
Exactly right.
完全正确。
All right.
好的。
And obviously we saw how Robert lied to Bill by saying that their good friend, that their
显然我们看到罗伯特对比尔撒了个谎，说他们的好朋友，
good friend Frank had passed away.
他们的好朋友弗兰克去世了。
And he said, are you serious?
然后他说，你是认真的吗？
No, I'm just yanking your chain.
不，我只是在逗你玩。
Okay, so this might sound very strange to a lot of you because a chain is something
好的，这对很多人来说可能听起来很奇怪，因为“链子”这个词
that doesn't really seem to fit in this conversation.
似乎不太适合这个对话。
But yanking your chain, remember this as a phrase, it means I'm just joking.
但“yanking your chain”，记住这是一个短语，意思是我只是在开玩笑。
Right.
对。
I'm not serious.
我不是认真的。
I'm just kidding.
我只是在开玩笑。
I'm lying to you, I guess.
我是在骗你，我想。
Right.
对。
So, but how can you use this in another context?
那么，你怎么在其他语境中使用这个呢？
Okay.
好的。
I could say, you know what, Marco, I have something I have to tell you.
我可以说，你知道吗，马可，我有件事要告诉你。
And I say what?
然后我说什么？
I'm leaving EnglishPod.
我要离开EnglishPod了。
I quit.
我辞职了。
I'm sorry.
对不起。
Are you serious?
你是认真的吗？
No, I'm just yanking your chain.
不，我只是在逗你玩。
Okay.
好的。
Or no, I'm just kidding.
或者不，我只是在开玩笑。
Right.
对。
So you're kind of teasing someone when you do this, right?
所以你这样做的时候是在逗某人，对吧？
I'm just yanking your chain.
我只是在逗你玩。
I'm just lying to you.
我只是在骗你。
I'm teasing you.
我在逗你。
I'm making you believe something that isn't true.
我让你相信一些不真实的事情。
Exactly.
正是如此。
So this is something you can use after you tell someone that you were just joking.
所以这是你在告诉别人你只是在开玩笑之后可以用的。
So I'm just yanking your chain.
我只是在逗你玩。
I'm just joking with you.
我只是在跟你开玩笑。
That's right.
没错。
You can't translate it directly or literally because it's not going to make sense.
你不能直接或按字面翻译，因为那样说不通。
So just remember this as a phrasal verb or a phrase in general.
所以就把这个当作一个短语动词或整体短语来记吧。
Exactly.
正是。
All right.
好了。
Let's listen to our dialogue one last time and we'll be back to talk a little bit more.
我们最后再听一遍对话，然后回来再聊一会儿。
I hate coming to high school reunions.
我讨厌参加高中同学聚会。
It'll be great, honey.
会很好的，亲爱的。
We will get to see your old classmates and catch up to see how they've been doing.
我们会见到你的老同学，聊聊他们最近怎么样。
Yeah, I guess so.
嗯，我想是吧。
Oh, look, there's Robert Matthews.
哦，看，那是罗伯特·马修斯。
Rob.
罗布。
Hey, Bill.
嘿，比尔。
Wow.
哇。
Great to see you.
很高兴见到你。
Likewise.
我也是。
It's been a long time.
好久不见了。
This is my wife, Dorothy.
这是我妻子，多萝西。
Pleasure to meet you.
很高兴认识你。
So Bill, how have you been?
那么比尔，你最近怎么样？
Can't complain.
没什么可抱怨的。
We have two children who are in college and my business is going well.
我们有两个孩子在上大学，我的生意也还不错。
How about you?
你呢？
Ah, you know me.
啊，你知道我的。
I'm a dedicated bachelor.
我是个坚定的单身汉。
I never married, although I do have a beautiful daughter with Mary.
我从来没结过婚，虽然我和玛丽有一个漂亮的女儿。
You remember her.
你还记得她吧。
We were high school sweethearts.
我们高中时是情侣。
It didn't really work out between us, but I really can't complain either.
我们之间没成，但我也没什么可抱怨的。
That's good.
那挺好的。
Have you seen Frank?
你见过弗兰克吗？
I was hoping he would come tonight.
我本来希望他今晚能来。
You didn't hear?
你没听说吗？
Frank passed away last year.
弗兰克去年去世了。
Are you serious?
你说真的吗？
Nah, I'm just janking your chain.
不，我只是在逗你玩。
He'll be here soon.
他很快就到。
I saw him last week.
我上周见过他。
He told me he would show up.
他告诉我他会来的。
All right, so we're back and talking about high school reunions.
好了，我们回来了，继续聊高中同学聚会。
These are very popular in the United States, right?
在美国，这种聚会很流行，对吧？
They are very popular and I think people often have them every five, ten, fifteen, twenty
非常流行，我觉得人们通常每五年、十年、十五年、二十年
years, but most people don't go to the high school reunion until either ten or twenty
办一次，但大多数人直到高中毕业十年或二十年后
years after their high school graduation.
才会去参加同学聚会。
Why is that?
为什么？
I think five years is very soon.
我觉得五年太早了。
Ten years is nice because you haven't seen people, but twenty years is really, I think,
十年不错，因为你很久没见人了，但二十年我觉得真的
shocking because people can be completely different or they could be the same, but it's
很震撼，因为人们可能完全变了，也可能没变，但
been, you know, you were eighteen when you graduated high school.
你知道，你高中毕业时才十八岁。
Now you're thirty-eight years old.
现在你三十八岁了。
You have this whole life that you've had and so I think it's much more interesting.
你经历了整个人生，所以我觉得更有意思。
Yeah, it's very interesting and I guess people go to these things half because they do want
是啊，很有意思，我觉得人们去参加这些活动，一半是因为他们确实想
to maybe meet up with old friends that they haven't kept in touch with.
见见那些没保持联系的老朋友。
I think especially this was very popular before the whole internet revolution.
我觉得在互联网革命之前，这种聚会特别流行。
Now everyone's in touch on Facebook and emails and it's just so much easier to keep in touch,
现在大家都在脸书和邮件上联系，保持联系容易多了，
but before you have to remember that it was basically by telephone or by mail, so actually
但以前你得记住，基本上只能靠电话或信件，所以实际上
seeing a person ten years or catching up with them was very difficult back then.
十年后见到某人或跟他们叙旧，那时候非常困难。
Yeah, we all see photos and videos now of our classmates, so it's not quite as surprising
是啊，我们现在都能看到同学的照片和视频，所以后来
when we bump into them later, but I think it is still interesting though because at
偶然遇到他们时，没那么惊讶了，但我还是觉得挺有意思的，因为
least on my social networking websites there are a lot of people that I don't have connections
至少在我的社交网站上，有很多人我并没有联系，
to, and so I look forward to my high school reunion when I get to see some of these people
所以我期待我的高中同学聚会，能见到其中一些人，
and kind of find out what they've been doing for the past ten or fifteen years.
了解一下他们过去十年或十五年都在做什么。
It's actually very interesting I guess when you see how your classmates have changed,
看到同学们的变化，其实挺有意思的，
how maybe the one that used to be the nerd or maybe not very attractive all of a sudden
比如以前的书呆子或不太有魅力的人，突然
is really attractive and has like a supermodel as a wife or how these things work out.
变得很有魅力，娶了个超模老婆，或者事情就这样发展。
Or the high school football captain is now kind of sad and fat.
或者高中橄榄球队长现在变得又惨又胖。
So yeah, these are the types of surprises that people look forward to when they go to
是啊，这就是人们去参加高中同学聚会时
high school reunions.
期待的那种惊喜。
So a very interesting subject.
所以这是个很有趣的话题。
Let us know on our website EnglishPod.com if your high school and the place where you
在我们的网站 EnglishPod.com 上告诉我们，你的高中和你住的地方，
live, do they have high school reunions or maybe even elementary school reunions.
有没有高中同学聚会，或者甚至小学同学聚会。
Yeah let us know.
是啊，告诉我们吧。
We hope to find out more about you guys' experiences and until next time.
我们希望能多了解你们的经历，下次再见。
Bye.
再见。
Bye guys.
再见，各位。